You might need to click as accept to being a panel, or host.
Do you want to kick off for us, Kevin, because we've only got 15 minutes for this?
Yeah. Hold on a second. I'll just have to...
Brent was going to do the intro, so hold on a second.
Let me-
Emma's on now.
And,
Brent.
It's me.
Hear you, Brent. Just can't see you, but that's okay.
Unless you've got-
I think you're better off that way, Chair.
Are you wearing a nice bow tie this morning?
On this occasion, I'm not, and that's better for you.
So I just don't have my camera. Why is my camera not on?
So-
Come.
All right. So thank you. See, I need this assistance, and you
guys are far more
skilled than I am in this regard. So can you see me now?
Yes, we can. Yep. Wave your hands if you want to open with a few points.
Okay. Let me just kick on, if I may. So, thank you, Chair, and members of the
committee. We really appreciate the opportunity to come along and talk to you
today. So on behalf of the Non-Bank Deposit Takers Association, thank you for the
opportunity. We'd like to focus on two factors today.
First, proportionality, and the second one is on capital.
So NBDTs have really strong regulation, our
prudential supervision, and a safe and stable system.
However, it remains important that the regulatory requirements reflect the size and
the scale of the institutions. This is really important. It does relate to us.
All of the banks are larger than us, so they have a bigger asset base over which to
spread the costs. As we're going into this process, there's no question that the
costs are escalating, and that's putting pressure upon all the new players in the
Non-Bank Deposit Taker Association.
So please, if you could, focus on proportionality.
Remember that things such as bank levy, doesn't seem like a lot of money, but it is
proportionate. It comes to us, it hurts, and it just adds to our
costs. And you know, it's like inflation.
We know that the costs will go up, it will creep, and very seldom will it go away.
So we want to really focus on any of those sort of, they seem insignificant,
but they are very significant across a smaller asset base.
General Capital is the parent company of my business. I'm the CEO of that.
We're listed on NZX. We have costs, and we have the ability to raise additional
capital. General Finance is the licensed body. They are the subsidiary.
And so we've got two levels of cost within that structure.
I do want to reinforce the fact that
if we do not make money, then the smaller end of the businesses will fail.
And we've seen what happens out of that. We've seen the bigger banks buy you.
And if you look at someone like Heartland Bank, which has three NBDTs in it,
virtually every bank around has got an NBDT in it, right from ANZ,
right down. So if you really want competition, if that is a
motivator in here, if we do want to get competition in the sector, we have to make
sure the costs are proportional and that we are able to gain
returns on our capital. If I look at the smaller banks, the return on the banks
like Bank of Baroda and Bank of India, et cetera, their returns are very low.
So, they would not be around if they did not have parents back in India.
So if you are serious, you do have to help us by controlling the
costs and by assisting us through that next level of control of costs.
We all know that the market is relatively concentrated here.
But if you look at the costs, if we all want to go and set up new computer systems,
the
amount of cost is absolutely massive.
I really implore you as a team watching over the Reserve Bank, that you are
thinking about cost as a major, major issue if you do expect this to
be successful over the next three or four years.
I'll pass now over to Kevin Hughes. Kevin was with us earlier and thank you.
Sorry to muck you around earlier, Kevin. I pass to you.
No, thank you, Brent. And, yeah, so hello, I'm Kevin Hughes.
I'm the CEO at Unity Credit Union. So we're a small credit union, sort of
headquartered out of Hawke's Bay, got about 35,000 members.
Following on from what Brent said, just want to highlight around the whole payments
infrastructure and open banking area.
So, with competition today, it depends not only on the ability to take on deposits
and provide loans, but obviously, also participate in the infrastructure that
enables customers to make payments and access modern financial services in a
secure, safe way. And that's really important.
So for smaller organizations like us, the access to that infrastructure is
technically feasible, but often not practical or commercially viable.
And I'd just like to highlight a couple of key examples that are recent examples of
this around how embedded pricing models that are traditional make it very
challenging for smaller organizations to get engaged in the payments and
transaction banking infrastructure.
And those traditional models are usually based on a fixed rate price and then a
variable on top. So I'll provide two recent examples. ESAS.
So we're really pleased that the Reserve Bank have made ESAS available to our
sector, and that's been certainly, part of that's been the influence of this
committee.
But it looks great on paper that it's theoretically available, but it's technically
not that easy. And the Reserve Bank have come up with a pricing model which
puts a fixed rate price before you even start.
And that has effectively meant that most of the NBDTs have decided it's
commercially not viable for them to be involved.
So fixed rate price, and that fixed rate price doesn't look very high, but that's
an example where for small organizations, every bit of this cost actually ends up
being disproportional. Another example is confirmation of payee.
Great initiative by the bank, through the banking association to set up extra
benefits and fraud protection for people making payments.
This was implemented without involvement of the smaller organizations that
effectively do exactly the same thing.
We've now got involved, but once we got involved, the pricing model for
confirmation of payee has a fixed rate price and a variable rate price, again,
making it largely uneconomic. Good news for us is that we've been able to negotiate
a better price, and we now have confirmation of payee.
But again, it's just there's still a fixed rate price in there, which is
disproportional for smaller players.
And then, of course, Brent's related to the prudential levy as well.
The Reserve Bank's preferred approach is to have a fixed rate fee and then a
variable on top. Once again, what you're seeing is any one of these things alone is
probably okay, but as you add all of these different layers up, you're adding a
fixed rate cost to the participation of small organizations.
I'm just conscious about time, so I've actually just...
So I suppose the key thing for us is that we need to ensure that embedded, what we
almost say would be anti-competitive pricing, effectively if we find a way to sort
of make sure that we can make sure that for organizations of a smaller scale who
play a really important role in New Zealand, have still got the ability to provide
those services for their customers and their members. I'll pass on to Emma.
Thanks, Kevin, and-
We've only got five minutes left too, so if you want some questions.
Yes. I'll keep it very brief. So I think I just want to round it out by
saying, what Kevin and what Brent are saying is that
there's been a lot of really good stuff happening, but the key is whether it works
in practice. So we do want to really acknowledge that real progress has been made,
the ESAS, the proportionality framework, capital settings, and use of the word
bank. Those are big deals for the NBDTs, and they will make a
difference.
But what we really need, and the question that you asked us was, what settings do
we want to see? We're really pleased with all the settings at a headline level, but
the detail needs to be continually observed.
And so that's our ask of the committee, is to see, so when these things are being
implemented, what is happening in practice? Are people using them?
Is it making the change that we want to see?
Because there will need to be constant monitoring and recalibration to make sure
that the detail, which is sometimes a little bit harder to keep interest in, but
that is really where the rubber hits the road.
So we'll leave it there, and please ask us any questions.
Thank you. We'll go first to Aradhana Williams.
Thank you. We don't have a lot of time, so forgive me for short questions.
First, to your point, Kevin, how much have you
been charged to access ECAS? We need some specifics about that because the
government accepted EPC's recommendation that the regulatory settings for non-bank
deposit takers should be a focus, and everyone's on board.
Yeah. So it's a $8,000 application fee, and it's $2,000 a month to participate.
Okay.
And again, that doesn't sound like a lot of money, but again, it's the cumulative
effect of some of these things.
And it's the initial setup cost that is, in your view, more problematic than the
ongoing cost?
I think the ongoing 2,000, because effectively we would only be using it a few
times a week, so if you work out a proportional per transaction cost, it's actually
quite high-
Yeah
... for someone like us compared to a second ANZ, for example.
So that's where it becomes problematic.
Understood. Okay. More general question.
There are still only 15 licensed non-bank deposit takers, I think, but one
new entrant in July. Are you seeing more interest because of those three changes
that the sector's been advocating for a long time?
Emma,
your question.
Yeah. Definitely seeing more interest in the last
couple of years since the Deposit Takers Act has gone through, and the use of the
word bank has really escalated interest, and we're seeing people from overseas and
people within New Zealand looking now to enter the market.
It's just it will take time.
Okay. So you're seeing a few of those new entrants, but we're not seeing that yet,
and a growth of about, I think 700 million in the sector, but you're still 0.4% of
total lending in New Zealand. What's it going to take to grow?
Do you think anything you've asked for today is the ticket?
If I may just jump in there. The real key is, if you're a lender, how do you raise
your capital? So do you raise it from another bank?
And so you'll know that Westpac are a very significant lender to intermediaries.
So
intermediaries get their facility from Westpac, then they re-lend.
So we're a non-bank deposit taker, so we actually take deposits from the public,
whereas other people raise it through systems like unit trusts, et cetera.
So I think that is good, healthy competition between all that sector to create that
tension. So it will keep going up, but it's still a limit on
what this sector will be able to raise, how much capital this sector will be able
to raise.
Thanks. David Wilson.
Yeah. Do you think there's any reason why would the world end with banks if they
were compelled to use fixed rates that are issued by the RBNZ?
I think it would get very rigid, very regimented, and
I don't think you'd get the market reactions that allows that
flexibility for us to say, for example, do we want to lend money on AI?
Do we want to lend it for systems on AI?
So would the Reserve Bank or somebody else be a party who would price that?
I'd be very reluctant to see that occur.
Quick question from me, just on switching.
What would make it easier for customers to switch their deposit savings and lending
from major banks to
Sorry if I'm dominating this, but the key on this is when your deposit comes up for
maturity, you're looking around to see who will I invest with?
And you'll look at the interest rate, and you'll just go to one of those other
banks and have a look. And secondly, you'll see what term do I want?
So what advice do I need to say, "Hey, put this away for one month, or one year, or
five years," or whatever it might be.
Yeah, that's on the deposit side. What about the lending side in terms of the
mortgage markets?
Because we have fixed rate deposits, then we have to have fixed rate
loans as well. So to get the matching of that, we match exactly on that with a
slight skew to the front end. So that stops that sudden rush on your deposits.
Can I just add to that as well? One of the good things that is coming in from 1st
October obviously is the new risk weight settings under the capital settings, and
that's obviously been part of the influence of this committee as well.
So it's going to be really interesting to see how now we have to have alignment of
risk weights and, I suppose, an equal playing field with the main banks for
how each asset is rated. That's going to provide an opportunity for us to be able
to be more competitive, especially in light housing, and obviously now we've got
the introduction of new risk weights for small business lending as well.
That's going to effectively be a positive thing for our sector about us being able
to compete more and offer a more competitive product.
Yeah. Look, we're going to have to end it there.
Thank you so much, Kevin, Emma, and Brent.
Really appreciate your contribution to the third round of the inquiry.
Thank you.
Thank you too.
All right. We've got Revolut in the room.
Welcome, Ryan and Georgia.
No kidding.
Thank you both for joining us.
Thank you.
We have received your written submission.
If you have got some opening comments, you're welcome to them.
Please keep them short because I know there's some good questions already
circulating amongst committee.
Excellent.
Well, good morning, Chair and committee members.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak today.
We are, firstly, I'd like to say we're very supportive of the committee's
drive to ensure progress on the recommendations made at last year's review into
banking competition in the New Zealand market, and to bring greater innovation and
value to New Zealand consumers and businesses in meeting their financial needs.
I'm Ryan Brussenhan. I've recently joined Revolut New Zealand as our CEO.
With me today is Georgia Grange, who is Revolut New Zealand's chief operating
officer. Georgia established the Revolut business in New Zealand three years ago,
so has been on the entire journey. Revolut's mission is to simplify all things
money, and our vision is to become the world's first truly global bank.
We're building an app where customers can manage their entire financial lives in
one place. Ultimately, we want to make all things money easier and cheaper for
Kiwis everywhere. We've committed to invest 120 million into local
operations over the next five years, and have already hired 50 people locally into
the Revolut New Zealand business.
Globally, Revolut now has over 80 million customers and is active in 40 markets,
and we continue to grow strongly as our proposition continues to resonate in
meeting the needs of consumers and businesses around the globe.
As we have outlined in our written submission in answer to the committee's
questions, Revolut's core position is clear.
AOTearoa's banking and payments market suffers from a chronic lack of competition,
and we are supportive of the recommendations arising out of the Commerce Commission
and Finance and Expenditure Committee's reviews.
To achieve true market disruption, our priority should be empowering consumers
through strict open banking API standards and democratizing the use of their
data,
implementing risk proportional licensing, and establishing passporting frameworks
with trusted global jurisdictions like Australia, the UK, and the EU.
By addressing foundational governance such as the independent review that is soon
to be underway of Payments New Zealand and focusing on modern fraud overlays, we
can rapidly attract global innovation, lower merchant costs, and give Kiwis the
world-class financial tools they deserve.
Building a multi-year, expensive, centralized real-time payments rail is
not a silver bullet to increase competition
Rather than prioritizing the industry investment of significant capital to laying
new settlement pipes that consumers are not currently asking for, our priority
should be improving the governance mechanisms and uplifting our existing
infrastructure. And with that, we're happy to answer any questions.
Thank you. I'm going to start off with Dan Edwin.
Thanks, Mr. Chair. Thanks, Ryan and Georgia, for coming before us today, and we've
heard a lot about your business. We understand you've got an application to
become a registered bank in New Zealand, so best wishes to that.
This committee clearly wants competition. We're agnostic on the company.
We want greater competition in the sector.
So wondering if you could just outline for us where you enter markets
overseas. What's the kind of growth trajectory that you've experienced in your
company in terms of disrupting existing players?
So from going from 0% market share to, what is that?
Wanting to understand the potential for Revolut to disrupt New Zealand's business
in banking.
Yeah. Thanks, Dan. It's obviously different in every
market we've been in, but we generally enter with an everyday
spending type proposition to make it easier for customers transact.
The main vertical that Revolut has traditionally entered in is the travel segment.
So making it easier and simpler for customers to
undertake foreign currency transactions, and also spend and save on a
daily basis. So that everyday banking capability
is where Revolut has grown significantly.
In a lot of markets, as I say,
all markets are differently, and there's some stats from markets
like Ireland, where Revolut has very extensive
usage of the app, which Ireland is not unlike New Zealand in terms
of size and market structure. So I think it varies by market, but
as I said in my opening remarks, the proposition seems to be resonating
with consumers and small businesses, because it effectively makes their lives
easier.
You've just got registration in Australia.
Do you want to talk about
what's the plan there? Because I guess we're relatively similar markets and similar
structure of banking markets as well.
Yes. So Australia received their ADI license
in mid-July, mid-August, mid-July.
And
Revolut in Australia has been around a similar time to New Zealand, Georgia?
Revolut Australia, yes, two more years than we.
We've been live in New Zealand just over three.
Australia started their journey just over five years ago.
They, again, to Ryan's point, started in the personal payments and eFX space and
has grown significantly from there.
They've also entered into different products that we don't have in New Zealand
currently, like unsecured personal loans.
They've seen great growth with their business proposition there as well, helping
small businesses.
In terms of the competition that we see in terms of uplift for markets,
for instance, in Ireland, to Ryan's point, where two in three Irish have a
Revolut account, which I think has more recently gone closer to the 80% of the
market mark. And what we consistently see is
once Revolut is launching different propositions, others are coming to play in
terms of changing, whether it's their loyalty points, what they're offering, or
whether it's their potentially hit a cap in terms of how small businesses get to
access their savings accounts and things like that.
We do see a trickle-on effect in pretty much all markets.
We start to see those movements, and we're already starting to see that in New
Zealand as well, which is reassuring that we're pushing the boundaries to get
what's right for Kiwis.
And one final question, Mr. Chair.
What's one change do you think that New Zealand Parliament could make to make
it easier for companies like yourself to enter and to grow and to thrive in New
Zealand?
So I think the changes that are already underway are the right changes to make,
one. The
lowering of the capital requirement is a good change.
There's a number of good changes. As I said, the governance review that's being
undertaken in Payments New Zealand I think is a good change.
The opening of access to the payment system.
I know you said one, Dan, but they're all good changes.
Great. Thank you.
Very good. Ariana Williams.
Georgia. Delighted you're here.
Thank you very much.
Please get bigger.
We have been talking about you a lot with other people who have appeared before us,
and I guess the question that I've been putting to a number of the regulators is,
you've been knocking on the door since December 2024. Why is the moat so deep?
I know you're at the stage now where you're almost there.
So you've almost swum that moat. But please share with us some of the insight into
why, and you've entered so many global markets, and it has taken so long to get
through what should've been a relatively open market that was designed in the 1980s
at the height of sort of an open-mindedness to places like yourselves being able to
get in here.
So I think as you referred to the bar,
all central banks and regulators have a prime interest in ensuring
the financial stability of the markets they oversee.
So the bar for entering as a regulated entity is quite rightly
very high. And so
I'm not sure,
and we're very supportive of that obviously, and we want to be held to the highest
standard. So all those changes we just mentioned
that you have underway are obviously going to, all those things help.
There's no one thing, I think, to Dan's point.
I'm not sure there's one silver bullet.
But it's the whole ecosystem and opening that up and making it easier
to enter and operate within that ecosystem, which is, it's
many things. It's the open banking work that's being done.
It's enforcing those API standards so that people can actually move data around.
It's the lowering of the capital requirements.
It's all those things together actually will increase the openness and
competitiveness.
I'm going to run out of time, so I'll ask you specific questions.
It would be great if you could offer that personal loan and small business lending
product in the New Zealand market from day one. You won't be able to. Why?
So, as I said, our strategy is to start with everyday banking, basically, to get
customers used to using the app, help them basically with everything they're doing
on a daily basis. We are looking to launch credit cards very early
on. And that we're actually using the open banking rails to make that
application process really easy for consumers, and we'll be the first, I think, in
New Zealand to actually have an open banking-based
instantaneous credit decisioning process for that credit card application.
So that talks to one of those points.
You've been negative about real time payments in New Zealand.
Is that because you see it as a competitive advantage for yourselves having
invested in the system?
No. I wouldn't characterize it as being negative.
I'd say we shouldn't do that first.
There's other low-hanging fruit that could increase competition, such
as clarifying governance, leveraging our existing infrastructure before we go to
real time payments. And that's purely because the real time payments journey, if
you look at every other jurisdiction, is heavy investment and long lead times.
Right, members, we have got a little bit of flex this morning.
I know there's a few questions, so-
Just a short one.
Yes.
EB and Payments New Zealand have gone through some change over the last few months.
Have you observed a difference in trying to get licensed for the products that you
could offer in the next sort of 12 to 36 months?
The licenses that we are working through don't require the necessary
sign-off or approval.
Okay.
I think to the conversation around how do we open up competition, the conversations
we're having around Capital and ESAS and useful return bank are all good things,
but to be honest, not silver bullet.
Any competition is good competition, and we
obviously all want to see more Kiwi fintechs and payments company come from the
ground up. We, Revolut, recognize we come in with a global backing, which is
great and helpful for us to be able to push more of these products and experiences
into the market. Even with that backing, the idea of connecting them to ESAS isn't
necessarily going to be a game changer for us, which requires us to have
institutional banking relationships in New Zealand.
Therefore, we don't have any active licensing per se, applications open with
NB or payments New Zealand today. So no clear answer, admittedly.
There's no change that we've witnessed so far.
Yeah.
But until we get all these settings right,
we, yeah, can't move forward as an industry.
Is it-
Dr. David Wilson. Yeah, I'm going to put two things together here because you've
opened this conversation up. But from my perspective, look, my daughter was in
Ireland for a long time, and she used Revolut. And when I went there, I used Wise.
And at the time, I used Wise because I thought it was more safe.
And there has been, as you're well aware, instances where fraud has been active.
So I heard you say that you're looking towards more modern fraud systems, but
it's also related to the payment rails, which you just mentioned.
So I'm interested because the large part of your business is smaller amounts, fast,
convenient, and lower cost. So there's balance there, isn't there?
But I'm interested in the payment rails because addressing fraud will be really,
really important with that.
Yeah. And fraud is obviously a global industry
issue.
That's the first piece. Revolut, we've got an
incredibly active fraud strategy.
We've got a huge proportion of our workforce are in the financial crime space.
And because we're a technology-based company, we've introduced a very
large number of controls and fraud overlays into our proposition,
like AI scam intervention on calls when a scam caller is
calling. We've got nine card controls in place on the app, which enables
consumers a lot of control over what they can do and what levels of granularity
they could block at.
So there's a whole bunch of controls that we can introduce, and we're continuing to
introduce really quickly because we're a tech company, effectively.
So we can do that. The other piece of it is obviously,
a majority of the fraud is via social engineering rather than the technology or
the payment rails. And so that social engineering piece,
much of which originates from the large social platforms, is a
key entry point for fraudsters that we look to put controls in our
app that help mitigate against that risk.
Yeah. So you've got bit of red flags nowadays than maybe what you had
before.
And proactively putting that control in the consumer's hands so
it can flag things up for them, and they can intervene, rather than
having to reactively capture something after the money's gone.
And I think on that, in terms of where we want to see things move forward is fraud
is like an ecosystem problem. It's the social media platforms, it's the tech
companies. It's not necessarily the payment rail that's going to fix things.
It's how customers come onto making payments and how they're coming off that on-
and off-ramp. So there's faster things we can do to help solve for that in terms of
overlays, like what we're doing with confirmation of payee, that will help to
ensure more security for Kiwis. But the same focus
should also be on the tech companies, as we do with financial companies, because we
need to be all working together.
Now, Todd.
Oh, actually mine's a quick... You just touched on it then, because you're the
second someone today that's mentioned confirmation of payee.
But in relation to costs, I just want to get your view on that.
You're basically saying, "Good idea, but it costs a lot." The non-bank deposit
takers we've actually negotiated down the prices they're going to be paying.
But I just want to get your thoughts on that, because, yeah, sometimes these things
seem great, but there is actually a lot of technology cost to it.
Other markets do it cheaper. So if you've got any reflections on that, because
those kinds of systems I imagine are only going to continue.
Yeah, and this probably talks to the proportionality point I was mentioning earlier
on.
Yeah.
We've almost got a one-size-fits-all approach in New Zealand.
No matter how big the participant is, you get landed with the same cost.
So confirmation of payee, because we operate in a number of markets, obviously it's
a great initiative, and we're very supportive of it.
But the cost for us in New Zealand, the confirmation of
payee is more than 10 times as much as we're paying in any other geography for
confirmation of payee. So, I think it talks to some of the points we mentioned
earlier around that proportionality and also the
governance and the decisioning around some of those overlay capabilities that are
put in and how that's done.
And then just a quick follow-up. So because the other thing was, and you touched on
ESAS, I just want to get clarification.
You're not planning to have an ESAS facility, or?
Not never, but not now.
Right. And what about the cost of that?
Because that's the other question that came up again about the proportionality.
Yeah, I mean, obviously,
ANZ is our transactional banker.
Yeah.
So they provide our transactional banking facilities.
They obviously invest a huge amount in this.
So it's both the integration with the underlying infrastructure, that cost, but
it's also the ongoing operational running of those services.
Which again, is a relatively high barrier to entry
for newcomers to the market, and smaller players to
be able to actually stand that up themselves, even if theoretically they've got
access to the system.
No, that's useful, because there's two practical ways we can continue to discuss
with the
people putting those fees in place that they might need to adjust for, yeah,
different clients.
What are the costs of confirmation of payee for you?
Give me 10 seconds. I can look it up for you.
You can ask another one while you wait.
We can follow it up after. There's a fixed cost component, and there's a per
request component. So say if you were trying to transfer me $20-
Yeah
... and you put in G Grange and it declines because you didn't have
my full first name.
Yeah.
Then that will cost-
Oh, right
... six. It costs you two.
Yeah. It will cost, I think 0.6 cents.
Right.
And so then you try again, and you forget my middle name, that's another cost.
And it's okay. That's normal in most markets.
But yeah, we do see over 10 times the price.
And who's paying for that cost?
10 times the price.
We will pay.
Well, you have to absorb.
Yeah. But Revolut-
You have to absorb, ultimately, or-
It's a cost that we absorb.
Yeah.
We have to absorb. Everybody's going to do it differently in terms of players.
We're not going to sit here and complain about fraud and
scam prevention as a compliance cost.
It's something we all have to innovate in, and scammers and fraudsters are
incredibly smart, so we all have to get ahead of them, and we see that as a product
investment rather than a cost that needs to be passed on.
Thank you both so much for your time. That's been really insightful.
I'm sorry we didn't have more time with you this morning.
Yeah.
But it's really helpful as part of our inquiry.
That's cool. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thanks very much.
Thanks.
Look forward to learning
more about what else in New Zealand.